so I'm going to abandon the grief and
regret like in regard to the fear so the
object of fear is still there but I
abandoned the the grief in regard to
their whatever that object is and when I
start with that I lose the sight of
object of fear where are notice the the
grief being listen like it's ceasing but
by paying attention to the object of
fear anymore no I'm paying attention to
know about the the grief itself as I
mentioned before whatever you do you
shouldn't be it should not be rooted in
your desire to get rid of the
disagreeable aspect of that fear so
whether you could be because you could
be paying attention to the fear but
you're not trying to get rid of it well
no that's what I mean then it's a
problem then you can also not be paying
attention to fear pay attention to
something else because you want to get
rid of it and that's a problem so the
problem is no way you pay your attention
the problem is whether you're trying to
get rid of the arisen experience or not
whether you're overstepping your mark
because he has a reason on its own
so you want to train in regard to the
arisen phenomena that's enduring for you
you don't want to be replacing the
phenomenon trying to get rid of it or
prolong it or get the better one instead
that's not on you so whether you're
focusing on the fear whether you're
losing the side of the object of the
fear by looking at the grief in regard
to the fear that's all fine that's all
part of the same reason experience of
disagreeable in this case fear exactly
the disagreeable aspect of the pain is
still there if you stop resisting it the
disagreeable aspect will stop being
painful then it's just displeasing yeah
but that's that's that's easy too easy
easy to withhold no problem it cannot
overwhelm you but it's when you want to
get rid of the disagreeable aspect when
you basically when you crave in regard
to it that's why you suffer
yeah you don't suffer because of the
disagreeable you suffer because of your
craving trying to get rid of the
disagreeable yeah so what if like when I
see that that I'm craving to get rid of
it but then I see that I'm craving to
get rid of it
so I stop take a step back and I stop
trying to get rid of it yeah that's why
that's all you know when you here in
this like generic spiritual teaching is
just just accept everything there is
like it works in that initial manner for
people accepting everything obviously in
order for it to work fundamentally you
need to understand what it is but the
reason why it works is like a like a
blanket acceptance works because to the
degree that they were resisting it they
stop resisting it so it does provide
that a little relief but obviously is a
view of accepting everything it's wrong
because there are certain things that
you already accept so then the attitude
of just accept everything was gonna
double down you're accepting as in
things that are pleasing things that are
agreeable things that you actually want
more than they actually are that's what
is the viewer accept everything is wrong
but it works relatively when people
resist something and then they accept it
through that even through that Bromfield
to that degree they were resisting the
stop resisting and to that degree the
experience relief but really you want to
accept things that you've been well
accept things to the extent that you've
been resisting them but not more than
that and you also want to resist things
that you've been accepting only to the
extent extent that you've been accepting
them but not more than that again it's
not something it comes down to training
your mind as I just just explained it so
something you can like catch him one
moment or two but by by paying attention
to that which is which your mind wants
and we
your mind doesn't want and when I say
pay attention I mean like being mindful
of not trying to attend every second of
it but be mindful of the reason
experience enduring sometimes for a
whole day you might have a whole same
mood present in the morning in the
evening for five days doesn't matter so
you want to be discerning that and then
stop resisting it on that peripheral
general background level like if you're
in a bad mood say disagree like bad mood
is bad only because you're resisting the
disagreeable aspect of it
it's a disagree and then why is it
disagreeable because you don't want it
so you keep fueling it in itself you
don't have to but I warn the pain no you
just have to stop resisting it because
it's nothing to do with you to begin
with and that can become apparent if you
give if you if you if you're able to
create some space for your mind to move
around that's why the view is the most
important thing if your view is I must
accept everything
I must deny everything or I must look at
everything attend to everything one two
three four not miss a moment not miss a
moment there is no space there to move
there is no space to reflect and you are
acting as if as I said as if your own
mind is your own if you're all mine were
your own as I said a simple decision a
determination to do something would be
enough for you to do it or to stop doing
it if you have a full say on the way
your mind works all you have to do is
say no once and that will be cemented
you wouldn't experience discrepancy you
wouldn't experience the pressure you
wouldn't you wouldn't need to restrain
yourself but you have mind has a mind on
its own mind is a separate animal mine
is a sixth sense doesn't listen to you
so you want to train it and you train it
by teaching it right from wrong if you
keep interfering and yanking its train
even when it's not doing anything that's
rooted in greed aversion delusion it's
not doing anything that's wrong yet you
keep yanking it then it will think that
no greed no diversion no delusion is
also wrong because you keep punishing it
for whatever it does that's how the
meditation techniques work people just
keep interfering with everything through them
interfering with everything through them
observance of the meditation technique
that's watching in just mechanical it's
like you mechanically tried to train an
animal it doesn't work like that so
that's the simile of the bull as I
started speaking on it just finish it
now you your bull is just what goes
everywhere eats other people's grass
other people's fruit and that's a
problem so you bring you down to your
own ground where it can be when it can
move around when it can't find the food
and then you keep an eye on it just so
that it stays on your ground so you
don't allow it to go further when it's
not supposed to where you will lose the
sight of it lose control of it but what
people do is people chained the bull and
then if the bull moves left they pull it
right if it moves right it pull it left
they to feel with every thought with
everything that arises so then that bull
doesn't know what to do
you keep attacking it for whatever it
does and then it cannot differentiate
good from bad but if you let the bull
say he moves to the left but it's still
within your field it's fun moves to the
right that's it
then you knows okay I can move here I
can move here then it goes a step
further into another then when you hit
it then you realize it's not okay so
it's not if I move the left or if I move
right it's how far left and how far
right I go and eventually learns and
eventually you will know I don't have to
look at it anymore
it will not go where I trained it to not
go that's what I mean like even peoples
meditation practice should revolve
around discernment peripheral
mindfulness from which you have the
perspective no this is still fine there
is no greed aversion delusion involved
stop trying to interfere
stop trying to stop thinking or whatever
of people do today let it in you we talk
to each other means thinking and
pondering means there is space for
thoughts to move to arise to present
themselves
right next something here was that he
got through this paragraph it basically
talks about not be the saying that
thinking and pondering for too long can
be tiresome for the body so the two
kinds of thoughts module 19 so BIC was
whatever a big who frequently thinks and
Ponder's upon that will become the
inclination of his mind if he frequently
thinks and Ponder's upon thoughts of
sensual desire he has abandoned the
thought of renunciation in order to
cultivate the thought of sensual desire
then his money collides thought sensual
desire he frequently thinks empandas
about upon thoughts of ill will thoughts
of cruelty he's abandoned the thought of
not cruelty and he will his mind will he
cried over the cruelty just as in the
last month of the rainy season in the
autumn and the crops thickened a cowherd
would guard his cows by constantly
tapping and poking on inside and there
with this stick check to check and curb
them why is that because he sees that he
could be flogged in prison fine or
blamed if he let him stay into the crops
so - I saw the unwholesome states danger
degradation deferment so if the mind
starts leaning towards the unwholesome
states that's when you poke it hit it
back so he doesn't go there
he doesn't welcome it he says as i
abided as diligent hardened resolute the
thought of renunciation around rosin it
understood the thought of renunciation
has arisen in me this does not lead to
my own affliction or to the others
affliction nor to the friction of both
innate wisdom does not cause difficulty
and leads to Nibbana if I think and
pondered upon this thought even for a
night even for a day even for a night
and day I see nothing to feel from it
exactly so you can think it I finished
all finished you can think it as much as
you want it because it's within the
boundaries of wholesome it's within the
domain of renunciation it's non your
will non-centrality wilted but with
excessive thinking pondering I might
tire my mind and body when the body's
tired the mind becomes trained when the
mind is trained is far from composure
so I studied my mind eternally quietly
brought brutal singleness composed it
why that so they my mansion will be
strained so see your problem here is
that you read this last bit and now you
question everything before you calm your
mind once you have fully established it
upon the proper thinking of the domain
of renunciation in other words by all
means overthink renunciation when that
gets reaches fulfillment then you will
see them oh actually I can carry this
further whereby I won't have to think
and be equally steady and calm if you
develop thoughts of renunciation fully
properly then you can start thinking
about composing your mind internally
quieted and growing bring it to
singleness not before so in other words
you can develop second jhana once you
fully developed first so yes from the
point of view of second jhana first
jhana is tiresome its course that's
that's exactly how the description goes
no the course falls off think the course
thinking and pondering has been subsided
but not from Pluto Jana's mind or from a
non jhana point of view the first jhana
is more than enough for our dimension
and yet that's exactly suitors like this
when people would read you read this bit
how case I must stop my thinking because
that's tiresome then will become
tiresome only once you fully be drawn
from sensuality from ill-will from
cruelty when you spend a night thinking
about the renunciation then you will
realize that actually I don't have to do
even this anymore
because he got so developed now I can
quiet it and bring the mind to that
unification point that's I mean by all
means think the night about renunciation
because the Buddha said yourself the
thought of renunciation has arisen me it
does not lead to a friction there's not
lead to a fiction of the others does not
cause difficulties leads to Nibbana
which means you don't need to go to the
second method then he says I quiet it
instead it dead in its every to Nevada
but then you also realize I might as
well go
on an even more pleasant way because
this is already Pleasant from the point
of view of being flogged in prison
blamed by sensuality you free from
danger of sensuality first John is very
pleasant but from a point of your second
channel where Jonna first Jana is course
to any course how do we find at all but
failing to see that there is the order
of development it's like the the suitor
of that simile of the cow where the
Buddha said the cow think so let me go
to the pastures I haven't been before
but before it steadies on the first
stone in the mountain where he starts
climbing he wants to step on the second
one and then falls in between the two
and it's like among starts thinking
about the second jhana before he even
fully understood and developed a theme
of the first jhana and then he doesn't
get any and that's exactly what happens
okay so this suits my view now I must
stop thinking and then you forget
everything else to read beforehand which
is like seven paragraphs of talking how
to think rightly in order to arrive at
the point from which you can see the
value of composure without a thought but
not before that he goes into Jonathan in
a few periods goes in exactly what I'm
talking about now yeah I thought he's
gonna talk about different things but
actually no it just went the same way I
just said it he went to Jonas and the
suti cook two kinds of thought not two
kinds of you must stop thinking it's
right thinking and wrong thinking
suppose I divide my thoughts into two
classes then I set on one side thoughts
of sensual desire evil and cruelty and
on the other side thoughts of
non-central desire no Neil will end on
cruelty you apply the effort when
necessary so you pull that bull you poke
it you hit it with a stick when it goats
to it when it goes to a sensuality are
willing cruelty not when it doesn't if
it's within nonsense art in only you
will know cruelty great leave it leave
it let it be that's how it develops
peace
whenever the food of sensual desire
arose in me I've done away with it
I never thought of your will cruelty
I've done away with it so even if you
take this suitor to mean that you enter
the first jhana upon composing your mind
that's done after your mind has been
fully cultivating only the wholesome
domain of thought in other words you
can't even conceive how you would study
the mind in the first jhana
unless you fully abandon the unwholesome
thoughts first through thinking
wholesome thoughts because some it's not
quite clear from this the way this
translation listed but either way either
way what I said there is the order to it
it's the same principle so you can't
start like oh I'm gonna compose my mind
in the jhana without having done away we
don't hold some thoughts and cultivated
wholesome thoughts without basically
learning how to think properly then you
can start seeing what's more peaceful
now within this wholesomeness well it
would be really really peaceful if the
bull would just completely sit down and
stop walking even within the allowed
parameter of walking within my own
ground and that's how you bring it down
and then you can say that's the first
jhana then you can you can abandon
thinking about that bull there with the
second yarn and so on it doesn't matter
the point is you can't start composing
your mind properly unifying your thought
without having learning without having
to learn without learning how to think
properly beforehand in other words you
have to spend a night cultivating
thoughts of renunciation no nail will
non cruelty and again that's in itself
from the point of view of ill-will
sensuality and cruelty that is
effortless the only time you need to
the only time you need to
the effort is when there is the prospect
of sensuality ill-will and cruelty then
you make the effort to not delight in it
not welcome it not entertain further
thoughts upon it but whenever that
effort is needed you do it that's what
means diligent and ardent means you do
the work when work is necessary
three o'clock at night three o'clock at
night four o'clock in the oven for you
don't say I'll do it later
that means you're not diligent but
people would usually think diligent
means every second every second one two
three four I'm watching I'm watching and
watching and watching there's nothing to
watch don't watch it there is no
sensuality no evil no cruelty you see
the need arises because it's always on
you to accept it or not which means it's
always conscious you just need to be
mindful of it so from that point of view
renunciation not cruelty not your will is effortless
not cruelty not your will is effortless
it doesn't require any effort to not
engage with sensuality that's actually
default sensuality requires effort
it will requires effort cruelty requires
effort because people never understood
that they don't see it like that they
think the renunciation is the painful
aspect saying no hurts say no requires
effort but it doesn't say no reveals the
pain of that which you indulge with so
you don't show your mouths of the pain
the Annunciation is completely out of it
so once you fully develop that which as
I said it's peaceful from the point of
view of sensuality then you can ask
yourself oh can you be the more peaceful
yeah exactly yeah otherwise you'll be
just acting out of that sensuality
so in order to train an animal you have
to stop trying to control it whatever he
does only to control it pull it back
when he does things did I wrote it in
greed aversion delusion same with the
dogs here
who to shout at him all the time they
simply won't know what they're supposed
to do how can then your mind learn what
you want it to do that's what I mean
when I keep saying to allow your mind to
think allow things to rise to manifest
let them in do but keep a corner of your
eye as in is the sensuality arising from
this or not then you just again you
don't deny that it has a reason you just
draw a line you don't go there I will
not entertain this I will not welcome
this well even the losing of the sight
can be only lost on account of decisions
that you made they were rooted in greed
aversion delusion that's a mindfulness
here effortless and that's why ignorance
is always comes down to your choice
ignorant choice which means you stop
making ignorant choices mindfulness
becomes unshakable you're not mindful
when you are thinking a mindful of
mindful of mindful you're mindful when
your experience is free from greed
aversion delusion exactly that's why
that's the root of all the problem and
the solution to all the problem pristine
awareness and purity of the
concentration all that is just wishful
thinking you remove greed aversion delusion you
you remove greed aversion delusion you
are automatically mindful even if you
don't call it mindfulness call it
whatever you want
means the clarity is there yes they
might manifest themselves on their own
but then you decide to engage always say
me doubt you
were not strong enough to not engage
without and again you can't just say
tell yourself I will not engage with
this by default you'll engage with it
you want to start including that initial
engagement in that doubt in that
mindfulness as belonging to that doubt
not belonging to you and that's how you
can at anytime at any part of that
engage doubt you can step outside of it
that's how we can abandon hindrance
perpendicularly at any given point
included in the arisen phenomenon tell
you a mindful of and then that what you
stopped entertaining a few early
and you have a choice shall I stay then
with this general general context
general picture or shall I give in an
attempt to the aspect of the doubt that
wants me to think further about it and
then you choose your powers you if you
if you if you let it it's like somebody
coming in front of a door they can't
come in unless you let them in they can
be shouting they're trying to provoke
you from the outside but you're the one
who then chooses to step outside and get
engaged with them or invite them in and
get engaged with them they can't do it
by themselves and then when you
recognize that that's what a confidence
arises from it as you can have the whole
world shouting at you trying to make you
doubt but you know where the doubt is
religion you understood it you went
beyond its nature
that's wit said sotapanna can have the
whole world saying the buddha was wrong
he will know that they are wrong you
know for petitioner point of view that
just sounds like religious
fundamentalism but in a way it is it's a
right fundamentalism its fundamentalism
that's according to the universal
principles it's according to Adama and
by all means everybody should develop it